OK.
OK.
Now that we understand the aggregation framework, we can
Ahora que comprendemos lo que es el Aggregation Framework
go through some common SQL examples and see how they map
podemos ver ejemplos comunes de SQL y cómo se relacionan a
to Mongo DB.
MongoDB.
Now these are in the documentation and I'm not
Éstos están en la documentación y no
going to go over all of them, but I'll go over
voy a repasarlos todos, pero veamos
just a couple of them.
un par de ellos.
This is in the same page, the SQL to aggregation framework
Esto está en la misma página que el recuadro de cómo se relaciona
mapping chart.
SQL al Aggregation Framework.
We assume that we have a Mongo DB collection
Asumimos que tenemos una colección en MongoDB
that contains orders.
que contiene pedidos.
They have line items in this array right here.
Tiene unidades en este en este array aquí.
So you can see the line items for the order are in this
Puedes ver que las unidades para este pedido están en
array with SKU, quantity, and price.
este array con SKU, cantidad y precio.
And there's also the overall order info right here very
Y también está la información general sobre el pedido,
naturally kept together in one document.
naturalmente junta en un solo documento.
In the world of SQL, this would be three tables.
En el mundo de SQL, esto estaría en tres tablas.
There'd be an orders table that would have this outermost
Habría una tabla "orders" que tendría esta
information.
información acá.
They'd have an order line items table that has this
Una tabla "order_lineitem" que tendría esta
information.
información.
And then there'd be a table tying it together probably
Y luego habría una tabla que juntaría todo probablemente
order line item, item order ID, which you could use to
"order_lineitem.order_id" que usarías para juntar
join those two tables together to tie the line
estas dos tablas para relacionar
items to the orders.
las unidades con los pedidos.
So let's say I wanted to count the number of orders.
Digamos que quiero contar el número de órdenes.
The way that would work in SQL is just select
La manera en que funcionaría en SQL es simplemente hacer
count star from orders.
SELECT COUNT * de "orders".
And if I wanted to do it in Mongo DB, now there is
Y si quiero hacer eso en MongoDB, tenemos
actually a count command.
un comando "count".
So we could just do db.orders.count.
Así que hacemos "db.order.count",
But to keep in the spirit of the aggregation framework
pero adheriéndonos al espíritu del Aggregation Framework
we'll do it this way.
lo vamos a hacer de la siguiente manera.
We're going to aggregate grouping on something we
Vamos a hacer "$group" de acuerdo a algo que no hemos
haven't done before.
usado antes.
the group is going to be on null.
El "$group" va a ser sobre null.
And then we're going to count indicate a new count
Luego vamos a contar con una nueva clave
key with sum one.
y sumar uno.
I think this is just to show you how it maps.
Esto es simplemente para mostrarte cómo se relaciona,
Although it might not be exact way you do the calculation.
aunque no vaya a ser exactamente la manera en que lo calcules.
You probably use the count.
Probablemente usarías "count".
I would probably just called the order account on the
Yo probablemete hubiese utilizado "count" en
orders collection to get this particular piece of
colección "orders" para obtener esta información
information.
en particular.
Next one is, let's see what the sum of the price is across
Lo siguiente es, veamos cuál es la suma de los precios de
all the orders.
todos los pedidos.
sum price from the orders.
SUM(price) FROM orders.
That's the SQL expression right there.
Ésa es la expresión SQL.
I can do that using aggregation.
Puedo hacer eso usando agregación.
Again I'm going to group by underscore id null.
Una vez más voy a agrupar de acuerdo a _id null.
And this time, there is no other way to do it that I know
Esta vez no hay otra manera de hacerlo que yo sepa así que
of so this is useful.
esto es muy útil.
You group by underscore id null, and then every single
Agrupas por _id null y luego cada documento
document's going to get aggregated to
va a ser agregado al mismo
the same result document.
documento en el resultado.
And we're going to calculate the running total, which is
Y vamos a calcular el total, que es la suma
the sum of the prices.
de todos los precios.
Now, let's skip forward a little bit and figure out one
Ahora, saltemos hacia adelante un poco y veamos uno que
that actually uses an unwind so you can see
use un "$unwind" para que
what that looks like.
veas cómo funciona.
So here's one that uses an unwind.
Aquí hay uno que usa un "$unwind".
what we're doing here is we're unwinding this collection on
Lo que vamos a hacer aquí es hacer "$unwind" en esta colección
the items and then we're grouping to by the customer ID
sobre las unidades y luego agrupar por el ID del cliente
and figuring out how many items they purchased.
y averiguar cuántas unidades ha comprado.
So this is the number of unique line items that a
Éste es el número de unidades únicas que un
customer purchased.
cliente compró.
That's pretty easy to express in the aggregation query.
Es muy fácil de expresar usando una consulta de agregación.
And then in SQL it's expressed like this, we're getting the
Y en SQL se expresa así. Obtenemos la suma de la
sum of a line item, that quantity and we're joining the
unidad, la cantidad y juntamos
orders table and the order line item table--
la tabla "orders" y la tabla "order_lineitem"--
this is the join where we join it--
este es el "join" donde las juntamos--
and doing it by customer ID.
y lo hacemos por ID del cliente.
So it's kind of different.
Es algo diferente.
To be honest now that I've been doing this for a while, I
Para serte honesto ahora que he estado haciendo esto un tiempo
almost feel like this one feels more natural for me.
me parece que esto es más natural para mí.
I can decode it more quickly than this one.
Puedo decodificarlo más rápidamente que éste.
Thinking about it as a pipeline makes it a
Pensarlo como un "pipeline" lo hace
bit easier for me.
más fácil para mí.
you can go through all these if you want on the page.
Puedes probar todos éstos en esta página, si quieres.
You should be able to reason out what all of these do now
Ahora que entiendes las diferentes partes del
that you understand the different parts of the
Aggregation Framework, deberías poder deducir
aggregation framework.
qué hace cada ejemplo.